Finding Aid for David E. Cole papers, 1951-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
David E. Cole papers
1951-2003
Cole, David E.
2010073 Aa 2
Chairman of the Center for Automotive Research (CAR) and previously Director of the University of Michigan’s Office of Automotive Transportation (OSAT). Collection documents Cole’s activities as the Director of OSAT and his consulting work.
48 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection came from David Cole (donor no. 9088 ) in January 2010.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
David E. Cole was a student at the University of Michigan, receiving a B.S.M.E. and Mathematics in 1960, a M.S.M.E. in 1961 and Ph.D. in Mechanical Engineering in 1966. He became an Instructor of Mechanical Engineering in 1965, an Assistant Professor from 1966-1971 and an Associate Professor of Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics in 1971. In 1978, Cole became the Director for the Office of Automotive Transportation (OSAT). He was appointed a research scientist at the University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute (UMTRI) in1991. While at the University of Michigan, Cole organized the annual Traverse City Management Briefing Seminar and was involved in the Joint U.S.-Japan Automotive Study. Cole retired from active faculty status in 2000. Soon after his retirement, Cole became a Management Partner of the Environmental Research Institute of Michigan (ERIM), which changed its name to Altarum in 2001. Cole took the position of the Chairman of the Center for Automotive Research (CAR), which was associated with Altarum. In 2003, CAR left Altarum to become a stand-alone non-profit.
An active member of the Society of Automotive Engineers (SAE), Cole was made an SAE fellow in 1986. He was a member of the SAE Board of Directors from 1980-1983 and 1985-1988. Cole served on various boards and committees within the SAE, including the Engineering Activity Board. In addition, Cole was the Technical Program Chairman for the 1988 FISTIA Conference. Cole was active in other professional organizations, and became fellow of the Engineering Society of Detroit (ESD) in 1990. In 2000, Cole received their highest award, the Horace H. Rackham medal. He was a member of the Air Pollution Control Association and the Society of Automotive Analysts. In addition, Cole was on the Board of Directors for the French-American Business Association and was the Chairman for the Automotive Hall of Fame.
Cole did consulting work for numerous companies and government agencies. According to a 1992 email recommending Cole for the medal of the French Order of Merit, he was a consultant in the areas of "vehicle design, internal combustion engines (emphasis on exhaust emissions and fuel efficiency) and strategic automotive industry issues." His many professional roles included the position of Chairman of Environmental Dynamics Inc. and also of the Automotive Consulting Group. Cole was President of Applied Theory Inc., a member of Johnson Controls Technical Advisory Group and of the Allied Corporation Automotive Technology Council, and a board member of Aero Detroit /Auto Dynamics. He was the Director of the Original Equipment Suppliers Association. Cole was also involved in the establishment of five Ann Arbor-based companies.
In his work for the United States Government, Cole served on the U.S.-Canada Free Trade Pact Select Panel, the Energy Engineering Board of the National Research Council and the NASA Space Systems and Technical Advisory Committee. He was a member of the Michigan Economic Development Corporation (MEDC) and was "appointed by Michigan's Governor to the Michigan Technology Tri-Corridor Steering Committee" (Biographical Profile from the University of Michigan). He also served on the Michigan Technology Council, the Economic Development Education Committee and the Michigan Environmental Review Board.
According to the SAE 1981 Ballot for Election of Officers, Cole's research interests included "mixture-motion effects on spark-ignited engine combustion, the development of thermal reactors for emission control, the development and testing of rotary and reciprocating spark-ignition engines, the photographic studies of flames, the optical measurements of both dynamic and thermal phenomena, the influence of vehicle maintenance and engine modifications on exhaust emissions and fuel consumption, automotive coolant evaluation and studies of stratified-charge engines." He also did research on the Wankel engine and studied manufacturer-supplier relationships. Later in his career, Cole focused on "strategic issues related to the restructuring of the North American industry and trends in globalization, technology, market factors, and human resource requirements," according to his biographical profile from the University of Michigan.
Over his professional career, Cole received numerous awards. In addition to the Horace H. Rackham medal, Cole was awarded the National Automobile Dealers Association Foundation's International Freedom of Mobility Award. He received Sweden's Order of the Polar Star in 1994 and was selected by Design News as an engineering leader. In 1998, Cole was named Marketing Educator of the Year by the Society of Marketing Executives and received the Rene Dubos Environmental Award. He received the National Order of Merit from France in 1999.
The papers of David E. Cole document his activities as the Director of the Office for the Study of Transportation (OSAT) and his consulting work. This collection contains nine series: University of Michigan; Associations and Government; Company Files; Correspondence; Research; Speaking Engagements; Publications, Papers and Clippings; Topical Files; and Audio-Visual Material.
Subjects:
Automobile industry and trade--Japan.; Automobile industry and trade--United States.; Bendix Corporation.; Cole, David E.; Consulting engineers--Michigan.; Earnst & Young.; General Motors Corporation.; Johnson Controls, Inc.; Joint U.S.-Japan Automotive Study.; Mechanical engineering.; Society of Automotive Engineers.; Transportation engineering.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Mechanical Engineering.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Office for the Study of Automotive Transportation.; Wankel engine.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- University of Michigan
  Cole received a Ph.D. in Mechanical Engineering from the University of Michigan, becoming an Assistant Professor in 1966, an Associate Professor in 1971, and Director of OSAT in 1978. This series documents Cole's professional activities at the University of Michigan, including his position as Professor of Mechanical Engineering and the Director of OSAT. The series contains information on the Traverse City Management Briefing Seminar, which was founded by Cole, and various projects related to the University of Michigan.
  - Mechanical Engineering Department
    The Mechanical Engineering Department subseries contains notes, exams and teaching materials for courses that Cole attended and taught. Videos from mechanical engineering classes can be found in the Audio-Visual Material series.
    - Courses taken
      - ME 180, 1960 (Box 1)
      - ME 465 -- Final and experiments, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Courses as a teaching assistant
      - ME 336 -- Teaching Materials, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Courses taught
      - "Undergraduate Automotive Engineering Courses," objectives for ME 496, 497 and 498 (Box 1)
      - ME 496
        - Teaching notes, 1960s-1970s (Box 1)
        - Exams, 1960s-1970s (Box 1)
        - I.C.E. (Internal Combustion Engines) test solutions, 1960s-1980s (Box 1)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - ME 497
        - Teaching notes and student tests/experiments (includes photos), 1960s-1970s; 2 volumes (Box 2)
      - ME 498 -- Automotive Engineering
        - Course notes and sample instructional handouts, 1970s (Box 2)
        - Class/lecture notes and student projects, 1970s-1980s (Box 2)
        - Problems and exams, 1960s-1980s (Box 2)
        - Exam solutions, 1960s-1990s (Box 2)
      - Vehicle Dynamics
        - Correspondence and miscellaneous, 1970s (Box 2)
        - Teaching notes (Box 3)
      - Summer course -- Low pollution Power Plant Systems, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
    - Professor Bolt's I.C.E. (Internal Combustion Engines) book (Box 3)
    - "Automotive Engineering Program, " with program requirements and report concerning education and research, January 1965 (Box 3)
    - Photographic roster of engineering faculty (Box 3)
    - Dedication of automotive and aeronautical engineering laboratories and report on engineering education at University of Michigan, 1957 undated (Box 3)
    - Centennial, 1986 (Box 3)
    - SAE student branch
      - Material by year, 1964-1971 (Box 3)
      - Outstanding Branch Award form (Box 3)
    - Photos of Cole and others (Box 3)
    - "Carsmith" paper by John A. Roby, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Office for the Study of Automotive Transportation (OSAT)
    Cole became the Director of the Office for the Study of Automotive Transportation (OSAT) in 1978. OSAT was originally called the Center for the Study of Automotive Transportation (CSAT) and was transferred to the University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute (UMTRI) in 1982. This subseries includes material on organizational planning (such as finances and strategic plans), meetings of the executive committee and information on the Automotive Quality Seminars, which were interdisciplinary luncheon seminars on automotive research.
    - Center for the Study of Automotive Transportation (CSAT) description (Box 3)
    - Organization information and strategic plan, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - Finances (Box 3)
    - "Review of Operations Through and Financial Plans", August 1980 (Box 3)
    - "Expense and Budget Review,", 1981 (Box 3)
    - "OSAT Review of Current Status and Future Financial and Program Projections,", 1982 (Box 3)
    - Automotive Quality Seminars (luncheon seminars)
      - 1980-1986 (Box 3)
      - 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - Review of OSAT (Box 3)
    - Executive Committee
      - Agendas, 1979-1981 (Box 3)
      - Minutes, 1978-1982 (scattered) (Box 3)
      - Minutes, agendas and memos, 1979-1982 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1979-1988 (scattered) (Box 3)
    - Visiting research scholar, Yoon (Box 4)
    - Delphi Forecasts, 1980s (Box 4)
  - Traverse City Management Briefing Seminar
    The Traverse City Management Briefing Seminar was a series of engineering and automotive conferences held annually in Traverse City. The seminar focused on future automotive trends and was sponsored by the Office for the Study of Automotive Transportation (OSAT). Cole founded the seminar, the origin of which was a one-day conference on the Wankel engine in 1972, and was heavily involved in the organization of the event. He was responsible for planning and chairing the seminars starting in 1975.
    - Seminars
      - Traverse City and Wankel Conference, 1972 (Box 4)
      - 1975 (Box 4)
      - Speakers for automotive seminars, 1977 (Box 4)
      - 1978 (Box 4)
      - 1987 (Box 4)
      - 1988 (Box 4)
      - 1989
        - Agenda (Box 4)
        - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - 1989-1990 notes (includes list of seminar themes from 1975-1989), 1975-1990 (Box 4)
      - 1990, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1991
        - Planning (Box 4)
        - Correspondence (Box 4)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - 1992 (Box 4)
      - 1997-2000 (Box 5)
      - Seminar brochures, 1973-1990 (scattered) (Box 5)
    - Speech summaries in UMTRI (University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute) Research Review, 1981-1994 (scattered) (Box 5)
    - Photos
      - Sent by Gib Butler (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Projects
    The Projects files relate to the various activities in which Cole was involved. These include the Clean Air Car Race, the Urban Vehicle Design Competition and the U.S.-Japan Automotive Project.
    - Clean Air Car Race, 1970
      The Clean Air Car Race was a race from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) to the California Institute of Technology, with the goal to increase public awareness of efforts to create low pollution vehicles. Winners of the contest were determined by a combination of performance, safety, low emissions and time. University of Michigan students entered two cars, a 1970 Volkswagen and a 1970 Chevelle, to compete in the internal combustion category. Cole's involvement in the project included overseeing student activities.
      - Rules manual and route guide (Box 5)
      - Rules and schedule of events (Box 5)
      - Participants (Box 5)
      - Reports on UM vehicle entries (Box 5)
      - Results (Box 5)
      - Correspondence (Box 5)
      - Photos of students and cars
        - Including UM students working on an entry (Box 5)
        - Including Fowler receiving a plaque with Professor Bolt looking on, and a picture of David Olds with VW entry (Box 5)
      - Chevy (includes orders and installation instructions) (Box 5)
      - Emission test (Box 5)
      - Vehicle Emission Test Data
        - Hot Cycles test (Box 5)
        - Hot Start 7-mode cycle test (Box 5)
        - 9 x 7 Cold test (Box 5)
      - Balanced Atmosphere Project (Box 5)
      - Organization Committee (Box 5)
      - Newsletters (Box 5)
      - News articles and clippings (Box 5)
      - Certificate of completion (Box 5)
      - Poster (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Urban Vehicle Design Competition
      The Urban Vehicle Design Competition (UVDC) was a student-organized contest to design and build a vehicle suitable for use in urban environments. The contest was open to students from U.S. and Canadian universities, and involved roughly 2500 students from 84 universities. Vehicle design goals included creating a car that would handle traffic well in urban areas, but that would also improve exhaust emissions, passenger safety, parkability, energy efficiency and low speed impact protection. The competition was an outgrowth of the 1970 Clean Air Car Race, and was sponsored by SCORE (Student Competition on Relevant Engineering). The University of Michigan contributed two entries designed by students in the ME 498 course taught by Professor Cole, the Urban Car 1000 and 1100. The Urban Car 1000 was a rear-engine, rear-drive car, while the Urban Car 1100 was front-engine, front-drive. This subseries includes vehicle drawings and blueprints.
      - General information
        - Summary of urban vehicle design project (Box 6)
        - Summary package (Box 6)
        - "Objectives, Activities, and Budget" (Box 6)
        - Rules (Box 6)
        - Entrance forms (Box 6)
      - University of Michigan entries
        - Summary of U of M project, including 1000 and 1100 design descriptions (Box 6)
        - Urban car mock-ups on photos (Box 6)
        - Urban Car 1000 design proposal, 1971 (Box 6)
        - Urban Car 1100 design proposal, 1971 (Box 6)
        - Vehicle drawings/blueprints (possibly for 1100), 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Vehicle drawings/blueprints and photo (Box 6)
        - Photographs and photographic slide of students and urban car (Box 6)
        - Urban car design evaluation (Box 6)
      - Students
        - ME 490 student progress reports, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
        - ME 490 student paper, 1973 (Box 6)
        - ME 498 (Box 6)
        - General student information (Box 6)
      - Final report, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Report on symposium "The Urban Vehicle in 1980", 1972 (Box 6)
      - SCORE (Student Competitions on Relevant Engineering, Inc.) (Box 6)
      - Expense summary, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Finances and orders (Box 6)
      - Correspondence (Box 6)
      - Newsletters, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
      - Clippings (Box 6)
      - LP gas offer and engine conversion, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Industry contacts (Box 6)
      - Safety (Box 6)
      - Engine (Box 6)
      - Chassis (Box 6)
      - SAE (Box 6)
      - Other schools (Box 6)
      - Urban Bikeways Design Competition (Box 6)
      - Report on Menasco compressible-solid shock isolators, 1970 (Box 6)
    - U.S.-Japan Automotive Project
      The U.S.-Japan Automotive Project subseries contains information on the Joint U.S.-Japan Automotive Study and the International Automotive Industry Forum. The Joint U.S.-Japan Automotive Study was formed in 1981 in response to U.S. demand for information on the Japanese automotive industry. The University of Michigan partnered with Technova (who was the primary supporter and sponsor of the study) to do research on technologies, practices, policies and relationship between manufacturers and suppliers of the automotive industry in both countries. The Center for Japanese Studies at the University of Michigan served as the U.S. Secretariat, while Technova filled this same position for Japan. This study resulted in a comprehensive report written in 1984. During this period, the University of Michigan held several US-Japan Automotive Industry Conferences (later called the International Automotive Industry Conference), where David Cole served on the Planning Committee. The Joint U.S.-Japan Automotive Study led to the formation of the International Automotive Industry Forum, which was established to promote "a continuing dialogue among major institutional participants in the Japanese and U.S. auto industry" and to "identify and clarify the major emergent issues confronting and leading to a restructuring of the world auto industry" (Statement on the International Auto Industry Forum, 1985). Another reason for the creation of the forum was to monitor the development of the industry in relation to the U.S.-Japan Automotive Study's final report. This subseries includes reports, information on meetings, and materials from the International Automotive Industry Forums.
      - Joint U.S.-Japan Automotive Study
        - Proposals, including "A Comparative Study of the U.S. and Japanese Automotive Industries", 1981 undated (Box 6)
        - Working papers, 1982-1983 (Box 6)
        - List of participants and researchers and participants' questionnaire (Box 6)
        - Correspondence
          - 1981-1983, 2 folders (Box 6)
          - 1982-1983 (Box 6)
        - Fundraising, with information on Technova, 1981-1982 (Box 6)
        - Finances, 1981-1982 (Box 6)
        - Research outlines, 1981; 1983 (Box 7)
        - Meetings
          - Meeting information and correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
          - Meeting information and international correspondence (includes research meeting), 1981-1982 (Box 7)
          - Researcher meeting and auto study group meeting, 1981 (Box 7)
          - Industrial sponsors and participants (includes research outline), 1981-1982 (Box 7)
          - Planning Group, 1982 (Box 7)
          - Researcher's Meeting, 1982 (Box 7)
          - Policy Board meetings
            - 1981-1982 (Box 7)
            - 1982-1983 (Box 7)
            - Final Policy Board Meeting (Box 7)
        - Press releases, press conference and clippings, 1981-1984 (scattered) (Box 7)
        - Human resources (Box 7)
        - Internationalization report (Box 7)
        - Demand for automobiles (Box 7)
        - Supplier/OEM relations (Box 7)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
      - U.S. Japan Automotive Industry Conference (International Automotive Industry Conference)
        - Conferences 1-5, 1981-1985 (Box 7)
        - Conference 8, 1987-1988 (Box 7)
        - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 7)
      - International Automotive Industry Forum
        - Forums
          - 1984-1985 (Box 7)
          - 1986-1987 (Box 7)
          - 1987-1988 (Box 7)
          - 1988-1989 (Box 7)
          - 1989-1990 (Box 7)
          - 1990-1991 (Box 8)
          - 1991-1992 (Box 8)
          - 1992-1993 (Box 8)
          - 1993-1994 (Box 8)
        - Correspondence, 1985; 1993 (Box 8)
        - U.S. and European Policy Board (Box 8)
        - Policy Board, 1984-1992 (scattered) (Box 8)
      - Japanese Automotive Information Center project, 1981-1982 (Box 8)
      - News releases and clippings (Box 8)
- Associations and Government
  The Associations and Government series documents Cole's activities in professional associations and government organizations. Included are materials from the Society of Automotive Engineers (SAE), government projects, information on hearing and testimonies, patents and individual organizations and associations.
  - Society of Automotive Engineers (SAE)
    Cole was an active member of the Society of Automotive Engineers (SAE). He was elected a Fellow member in 1986, and served on the Board of Directors from 1980 to 1983 and 1985 to 1988. This subseries documents his activities in SAE, including his role on various boards, committees and conferences. In 1983, Cole became the Chairman of the Engineering Activity Board (EAB), which oversaw various activity boards and reviewed technical papers, among other activities. Cole was the Chairman of the Powerplant Activity before becoming Chairman of the EAB, and he was also the Advanced Powerplants Committee Chairman. This subseries contains correspondence and meeting minutes from several boards and committees, including the EAB, the Membership Services Board and the Objectives and Strategic Planning Committee. For a complete list of Cole's positions within the SAE, please see his biography filed in the Company Files series under the French Trade Commission. Cole was the Chairman of the 1988 FISITA Technical Program Committee. Documentation on this conference includes correspondence, meeting minutes and information on session areas and papers. Information on later FISITA conferences can be found in the Topical Files series.
    - Boards
      - Engineering Activity Board (EAB)
        - Executive Committee meeting
          - September 1983 (Box 8)
          - January 1984 (Box 8)
        - Aerospace Congress/Committee, 1984 (Box 8)
        - Power Plant Activity Governing Board
          - 1977-1980 (scattered) (Box 8)
          - 1980 (Box 8)
          - 1981-1982 (Box 8)
        - International Planning Committee (Box 8)
        - Reorganization, 1983 (Box 8)
        - EAB report to Board of Directors, 1983 (Box 8)
        - "Year in Review,", 1984 (Box 8)
        - Meeting and honors convocation (Box 8)
        - Correspondence and miscellaneous about various committees and activities, 1983 (Box 8)
        - Correspondence thanking members, 1984 (Box 8)
        - Correspondence and miscellaneous, 1980s (Box 8)
      - Board of Directors
        - Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 8)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
      - Executive Committee Board
        - Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 8)
        - Joint meeting, 1988 (Box 8)
      - Technical Standards Board, 1990s (Box 8)
      - Industry Technology Advisory Council and Emerging Technology Advisory Board, 1988-1992 (Box 8)
      - Membership Services Board, 1990s (Box 8)
    - Committees
      - Socio-Technical Committee (Box 9)
      - International Coordination Committee (Box 9)
      - Objectives and Strategic Planning Committee, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Historical Committee (Box 9)
      - Productivity/Manufacturers Committee, 1983 (Box 9)
      - Ad Hoc Committee on Personal Computer, 1983-1984 (Box 9)
      - Government Assistance Committee, 1982 (Box 9)
    - Conferences
      - FISITA, 1988
        - Overview (Box 9)
        - Correspondence (Box 9)
        - Planning for Congress, 1988 (Box 9)
        - Congress packet, 1998 (Box 9)
        - Organization -- staffing (Box 9)
        - Session area descriptions (Box 9)
        - Technical Committee (Box 9)
        - Technical Committee and Awards Committee (Box 9)
        - Abstracts, paper and session areas/topics information, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
      - International Congress and Exposition
        - 1980 (Box 9)